Hi, I'm Coach Prep Conturus and this
video is going to discuss the military
press. So, the first thing about the
military press that I want to talk about
is range of motion.
I like people to start right here at the
top of the sternum and press overhead to
a complete lockout. Now, some people
have different ratios of forearm to
humorous length and they don't or they
just have, you know, tight musculature
and they have problem getting problems
getting all the way down. If it hurts to
go all the way down, don't go down that
far. But if you can do this painfree, I
like it to start right here. To me,
that's a a proper military press. And
also, make sure you lock out fully.
Don't stop here. Push that extra
distance. So that's range of motion. The
next thing I want to talk about
is your stance width and your core
function. So
some people like just around a narrow
like a shoulder width stance. Some
people go a little bit wider. Some
people offset their feet. And any one of
those is okay. I happen to like around a
shoulder width stance. Once the bar is
right here on the shoulders, you are
going to be leaning back slightly.
So, you want to make sure that your
glutes are squeezed and your abs are
braced. You don't want to be loosey
goosey in the core. This needs to be
tight. And a lot of as the weight gets
heavier and as the reps approach
failure, people tend to lean back more.
It's almost impossible not to. So you
want to have the muscles tight. So to
prevent that, you don't want to lean
back excessively when you do this.
And then another thing before I
demonstrate is I want to talk about the
scapula.
So normal uh scapulmeral rhythm is going
to look like this. The scapula upwardly
rotate.
Now, um there is some research showing
that the heavier you go, the heavier you
lift, the scapula don't rotate upwards
as much. Like if I just go like this,
they're going to rotate upwards a lot.
Whereas, if I have heavy load, they're
not going to upwardly rotate as much.
But you don't ever want to limit that
natural upward rotation. So, I don't
know if you can see my scapula here, but
you're going to have this normal rhythm
as you press overhead of your scapula
going like this.
And you don't ever want to interfere
with that. You don't want to think of
just these scapula sticking in place.
They're going to come overhead. Now the
next topic is related to that is um
how do you do you keep the shoulders
down or do you shrug them upwards as you
come up and this is a debate. So some
coaches think that as you come up you
want the shoulders back and down. Some
coaches think that you should drive the
scapula upwards. I think you don't need
to think about that too much. Do what
feels natural.
My shoulders will come up a little bit.
Gymnasts when they're doing their
handstand stuff, they shrug upwards. So
do most Olympic weightlifters. They
shrug upwards. Um but you don't have to
exaggerate it. Um you just just press
strongly and feel your scapula
supporting the muscles supporting the
load, you know. So you've got like
serrus anterior, lower traps, upper
traps. You've got these muscles in the
back that will help support the load. So
use those muscles.
And that's just a natural rhythm. And
then finally, before I demonstrate one
last thing, um, Olympic weightlifterss,
you know, when they pass their head,
they will drive their head forward. Once
the bar passes their head, they actively
drive it forward.
And I think that's the best advice. But
some of my powerlifting friends, they
don't do that. They stay like this
because they think that it transfers
better to the bench press. So that's
worth noting. So, not everyone drives
the head forward. All right. So, here's
what it looks like. I am going to grab
the bar. I'm not way out wide. I'm in
here. It's a pretty narrow grip, just
outside shoulder width. All right. Some
people like the false grip. Some people
like to tuck their thumbs. I actually
like the false grip here.
And I'm going to come down. My shoulders
are underneath. I am not starting up
here like in the front squat position.
My shoulders are my elbows are under the
bar.
Bar is just above my sternum.
I will
take it off the rack. Shoulder width
stance. Glutes are squeezed. Core is
braced. And now from here I am going to
have my lats are tight. My triceps are
tight. I'll explain what this means.
When I have the bar right here, I'm
squeezing my lat. I'm going to use my
triceps. I'm all this is tight in here.
It's not loosey goosey. It's tight. My
elbows are tucked inwards too a little
bit. Okay. And this
leads to the most of the of the load
being placed on the muscles. Okay. So,
right here, elbows under the bar. Lats
are tight. Everything's tight. Elbows
are tucked in. They're not flared out.
They're in like this. I press upwards.
Right when it passes my head, push the
head forward. lock out and notice my
scap leg come up like this. This is a
strong lock out. Come back down. So
again, here's what three reps looks
like.
As you will notice, I was not leaning
back excessively.
I used a full range of motion.
Everything was tight. And I did not let
my elbows flare out too much. Here's
what it looks like. If you take a wide
grip and have your elbows flare out too
much, you end up looking like this. See
that?
And that's
not optimal
in the long run. Um, it's just not as
easy on the joints. So again, let's
recap.
Shoulder width stance or an off with
stance. Okay. Uh, squeeze the glutes.
Brace the core.
Bar starts from the bottom position.
Lats are squeezed. You're going to use
your triceps. Elbows are tucked in.
Take a deep breath.
Explode upwards. The bar skims your
face. When it passes your head, drive
the head through. And this is when the
elbows will come out. You will
externally rotate right here and lock
out overhead with an active
active scapula there. Hold the lock out
and then reverse in the same exact
motion. Hope you like the video.